Today we have assembled in the area of Vishuddhi.
明善轮崇拜 美国纽约 1991年4月28日
In the Gita, Shri Krishna has described
在薄伽梵歌中 锡吕 克里希纳用领域（Kshetra）
the area as Kshetra,
来描述这个区域
and the one who knows the area is called as Kshetragna.
知道这区域的人 则是为领域的知者（Kshetratra）
Gna, yesterday as I told you, gna or gya, means:
昨天我告诉你们接近 额轮(Agnya)的意思是
"The one to know on your central nervous system".
这个喉轮使你们 在中枢神经系统中感知
So the one who is the knower of that area is the Kshetragna.
因此知道这喉轮区域的人 是警觉的知者（Dakshatatra）
Today we are going to know about the Hamsa Chakra.
今天我们要来认识 明善轮(Hamsa Chakra)
That is the area of, between the two eyebrows,
这是在两眉之间的区域
[SOUNDS LIKE 'RUKUTIS'], they have called it.
他们称它
This one is placed at the base of the brain,
这区域位于脑的底部
which is called as Mooldar,
称为Moorda
and this part is the complete controller
这部分完全控制整个脑的底部
again I say, base of the brain.
我要再度说明是脑的底部
And that is a part of the Visshuddhi still,
而这也是喉轮的一部分
which is an extremely important center
就人类的知觉而言
as far as the human awareness is concerned,
这是非常重要的中心
because these two nadis, Ida and Pingala,
因为当这两脉——左脉与右脉
part of them crosses over this Chakra of Hamsa.
它们的一部分是在明善轮交叉
So when the ego and superego develop in our brain
因此当自我与超我 在我们的脑中发展
and cover our limbic area,
并且覆盖我们的边缘系统时
from both the sides the strands
源自于喉轮的两股力量 便坐落在脑中
So they also control these two institutions from outside.
它们也从外控制这两个机制
For example, it crosses like this,
举例来说 从明善轮
goes up like that from Hamsa, and then some strands.
这股力量像左右这样地交叉 上升
and form ego and superego.
形成自我与超我
So from the back side, on top of them,
从后面看来 这两股力量
these two strands go and sit.
延伸并且端坐在头上
You all know that Hamsa Chakra gives you discretion,
你们都知道明善轮 是给予你们明辨是非的能力
but still we do not understand,
但是我们仍然不了解 何谓明辨是非的能力
The first and the foremost important center within us
首先 在我们之内 最重要的能量中心
is the Mooladhara Chakra.
是根轮
If we do not have the proper
如果我们对根轮 没有适当的明辨力
we get into wilderness, I should say,
我们会陷入狂乱不羁 无法达至平衡
or we open the doors of hell for ourselves.
或者我应该这么说 我们替自己开启通往地狱的大门
As you know, that only the Ida Nadi
你们都知道 只有左脉是源自于根轮
That means, it's the desire,
这个意思指愿望
power of desire within us, starts from Mooladhara.
在我们之内的愿望力量 起源于根轮
But it's not the mental, which is the Pingala Nadi,
至于心智思维方面 是在右脉
which starts from Mooladhara. It starts higher.
并非源自于根轮 它起始于更高处
So to have a complete understanding about..
我们要有完全的了解
The child is crying, please take away the child.
那个孩子在哭 请把那孩子带走
Yesterday, again the same thing happened, this is indiscreet.
昨天也发生同样的事情 这是没有明辨是非的能力
Continuing with the child all the time, yesterday was the same thing.
继续整天和孩子在一起 昨天也发生同样的事情
Immediately you should take out the child.
你们应该马上带走这孩子
In the meeting, if the child is crying, immediately take out the child.
在集会中有任何孩子哭泣 必须马上带走他
There is something wrong with the child, immediately take out the child.
这孩子有些地方不对劲 马上带走他
Again it's indiscreetion.
这是明辨是非的能力
So one thing one has to know, that
你们要了解
Mooladhara Chakra cannot be controlled
我们不能用心智的思维活动 去控制根轮
But if you shift it to the mental activity
如果你们将根轮变为心智活动
then the control over Mooladhara is completely lost.
你们会完全失去对根轮的控制
Apart from whatever has happened in the West,
暂且不谈现在西方所发生的一切
Mooladhara Chakra is all gone
根轮全部进入人类的心智活动中
It is so much discussed, talked.
它是如此被频繁地讨论 谈论
It is so much described, written down,
它是如此被大量地描述 撰写
so much read, so much put into our heads,
被大量地阅读 大量地放入我们的脑中
that it has become a mental activity.
以致于它已经成为了心智活动
So, Mooladhara doesn't act
因此 根轮的运作不再有 它所应具备的自然而然
That's why there are problems
这就是为什么有这么多人 无法生孩子
So many become impotent very early
这么多非常年轻的人就阳痿
because it is used not by the power of desire,
因为它不是由愿望的力量发动
but by mental activity - a shift.
而是由心智活动 转换
Now you see the light here, is burning there
现在你们看到这里有光
But instead of this oil, you put just water.
但是如果你不放油而只加水
Will it burn? It won't.
它会燃烧吗 不会
Because water is not going to nourish this light.
因为水不会滋养这光
So, the more mental activity you have,
因此 你有越多的 心智思维活动的话
your Mooladhara gets spoilt and it becomes uncontrollable.
你的根轮会败坏而变得无法控制
But if it is left to your desire,
但是如果把它转化成你的愿望
so it becomes spontaneous.
它会变的自然而然
This is a fundamental principle that is missing
这是在西方思想中
in the Western thinking, I think
所缺乏的基本原则 我想
that whatever is spontaneous,
任何自然而然的事物
they leave it to the mental activity.
他们都用思维去想
Wherever the mental activity is to be used,
无论何时要用到思维活动
you should use mental activity and wherever
你们就应该运用思维活动
you must use your desire power.
你们就必须运用你们愿望的力量
Also, it is spontaneous,
同时 这是自然而然的
though it should not be an obsession.
不应该沉迷它
Any obsession cannot be spontaneous.
任何的沉迷都不能是自然而然的
It's just, at a moment, you have the desire. That's all.
它只是 在某一刻 你有这愿望 这样而已
But all the time if there sits in your mind,
但是如果它占据你的脑海
that means you are using water to have the fire.
这表示你正用水去燃起火焰
Same about the Swadisthana Chakra.
同样地 关于腹轮
Swadisthana is for creativity. Anything you can create.
腹轮是创造力 你们可以创造任何事物
You can create a sari.
你们可以创造一件纱丽(sari)
You can create a beautiful design, pattern.
你们可以创造美丽的设计 造型
You can create a beautiful art of anything,
你们可以创造美丽的艺术品 或任何东西
but as soon as you put it on a mental level, it's finished.
但是一旦你们将 它放在思维的层面上 它就完了
Also in the West, too much discussion is about the art.
在西方 对艺术有太多的讨论
This is not art, that is not art.
这不是艺术 这不是艺术
This should not be like this, that should not be like this.
它应该要做得像这样 它应该要像那样
I mean, it's creativity, spontaneous.
我的意思是 创造力是自然而然的
Whatever the artist wants to produce,
无论艺术家想要 怎么做就让他去做
You cannot appreciate anything
任何事物被带到心智思维层面
So now, we have critics,
现在 我们有艺术评论家
and the artists are not spontaneous,
艺术家不再是自然而然的
they're afraid; they only think:
他们害怕 只在意
"What will the critics say?"
评论会怎样说
Even when I'm writing the book,
甚至当我写书
when I give it to some Sahaja Yogis to read, they say:
我将它给一些 霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者阅读时
"Mother, if You write it like this, then they'll say like this."
他们说 母亲 如果您这样写 那他们会这样说
I said: "Let them say, who cares?"
我说 让他们去说吧 谁在乎呢
So then, critics should criticize
艺评家批评
and say: "This is not all right. This is not an art
并说 这不好 这不是艺术作品
because this is such, this is such".
因为这样 因为那样
So the artists are finishing, art is finishing.
因此艺术家完了 艺术也完了
Now what is left are critics.
现在只剩下艺评
So now they don't know what to do with their profession,
他们不知道要用 他们的专业能力做什么
so they are criticizing each other.
所以他们互相批评
So we have only critics criticizing each other.
我们只有互相在批评的艺评
But there's no art now. What to criticize?
但现在没有艺术了 还要批评些什么
And art has to be now made into money.
而艺术现在要能赚钱
So the critics must certify.
所以要艺评去认证
It's so man-oriented, the whole programming of these critics is,
整个批评的运作模式 是如此人为导向
that it is never an art. You know, they draw one line
以至于永远没有艺术
and say: "Now this is art, all right".
然后说 好 现在这是艺术
If the critics say that it's art you had better accept,
如果艺评说它是艺术 你最好接受它是艺术
Then again mental: "It's a lonely person standing there" this, that.
然后思维再度运作
It should be spontaneous! Why to describe an art?
这应该是自然而然的 为何去描述艺术
So the mental level is so alert
心智活动是如此活跃
and is all the time trying to see things
无时无刻企图根据 某些标准去看待事物
All these norms are created about something
这一切标准放诸于 这些如此自然而然的事物
All bathroom culture is decided by the brain.
所有浴室文化都是由大脑决定
Nothing is spontaneous. It's such a joke, I tell you!
一点都不自然而然
So people become artificial. Art becomes artificial.
因此人变得不自然 艺术也变得不自然
Your Mooladhara becomes artificial.
你们的根轮变的不自然
Because it's all now man-made.
这都是人为因素
All the spontaneity is lost.
所有自然而然的都已经消失了
If you see any art from any country, just watch.
如果你们看到来自 任何国家的艺术品
Why must you react to it? Just watch, as Sahaja Yogis.
为什么你们一定要对它起反应
You should just watch
你们应该只是去观赏
and the whole thing will start flowing through.
然后全部事情会开始流动
Now this Greek tragedy of romanticism,
这浪漫主义的希腊悲剧
then the romance of Romeo and Juliet,
然后是罗密欧与朱丽叶的罗曼史
all is imaginary, is all mental.
这些都是想象的
And then you accept, accept only relationships
你们只接受那些人工化的关系
even between husband and wife.
甚至夫妻之间也是如此
Like the husband must bring a flower every day to the wife,
像丈夫必须每天带花给妻子
show her a flower, as if she's a priest or something.
献花给她 好像她是祭司什么的
And the wife must - I don't know
而妻子必须要
what they do all artificialities.
我不知道她们做些什么 都是矫揉造作
And then he must say "Thank you" ten times to her,
然后他必须对她说十次谢谢
and she must say "Sorry" to him a hundred times.
她必须对他说一百次对不起
I mean they're husband and wife,
我的意思是 他们是夫妻
left and right side of a chariot!
如同一部马车的左右侧
And then the men expect this should happen.
但男士期待这应该要发生
Women expect this should happen.
女士期待那应该要发生
Men expect the women should be like men,
男士期待女士应该要像男士
and women expect women, men should be like women.
而女士期待男士应该要像女士
Men are very particular about time, women are not.
男士非常讲究时间 女士并非如此
So women must be very particular about time,
所以女士必须非常准时
otherwise they think she is the worst person
要不然他们就会认为她是 他们所遇到过最糟糕的人了
The woman is, say, more particular about her kitchen
女士 比如说 对于她的厨房
or maybe about her dress.
或服饰上比较讲究
So the man would get angry with her
因此男士会因为 她花太多时间准备而生气
It's mutually so indiscreet
这两方都缺乏明辨力
that the relationship becomes absolutely absurd.
以至于关系变得荒谬可笑
There should be understanding that she is the left side
双方应该要彼此了解 她在左边
and you are the right side,
你在右边
and both of you have to act according to your nature.
你们都要根据你们的天性而行动
On the contrary,
相反地
you want to make somebody look so funny,
你们却只想要让某人看来可笑
because imagine a man becoming a woman
因为 想想看 男人变成女人
and a woman becoming a man. You see it's a joke,
女人变成男人 你们看 这是个笑话
but that's what has happened.
但这是已经发生的事情
Whatever the men are supposed to do they cannot do
无论男士该做些什么 他们做不成
and whatever women are supposed to do they cannot do.
无论女士该做些什么 她们做不成
Whatever the children are supposed to do they do not do.
无论孩子们该做些什么 他们不去做
For example, children in the West will go on asking: "Why?"
举例来说 西方的孩子会不断地问 为什么
Who are they to ask "Why?" What is their growth?
他们有什么资格去问 为什么 他们在哪里成长
What is their intelligence? What is their maturity?
他们的智慧在哪里 他们的成熟在哪里
They cannot be treated like a judge sitting in the court.
我们不能把他们当作坐在 法庭中的法官一般地对待
They are children!
他们只是孩子
But when they come to Sahaja Yoga
但是当他们来到霎哈嘉瑜伽
they lose their discretion.
他们失去了这明辨是非的能力
First, before coming to Sahaja Yoga,
首先 来到霎哈嘉瑜伽之前
the husband and wife quarrel all the time.
夫妻一天到晚吵架
Half steps are in the courts and half outside.
一脚已经踏入了法庭
After Sahaja Yoga they cling to each other,
来到霎哈嘉瑜伽之后 他们紧紧攫住彼此
so much like glued together, it's impossible.
就像用胶水黏住一样 这是不可能的
So much so that for the wife's sake
太过度 导致因为妻子的缘故
they will leave Sahaja Yoga.
他们会离开霎哈嘉瑜伽
They'll ruin each other like that. They're glued together.
他们会这般地彼此毁灭 他们紧黏在一起
Before Sahaja Yoga they neglect their children, don't bother.
来到霎哈嘉瑜伽之前 他们忽视他们的孩子而并不在意
After Sahaja Yoga they're glued to their children.
来到霎哈嘉瑜伽之后 他们紧紧黏住他们的孩子
Then nobody can say a word against the child.
没有人可以说一句 违逆这孩子的话
The child can go and hit anyone, you cannot say anything.
这孩子可以去打任何人 你们却什么都不能说
They'll ruin the child.
他们也毁了这孩子
So the discretion is lost completely in relationships,
因此在关系中完全丧失了 明辨是非的能力
whether it is sex, whether it is creativity,
无论在性 在创造力
whether it is family, anything.
在家庭 在任何事之中
That's the part of the Hamsa Chakra.
都是明善轮的一部分
Then we come to the Nabhi Chakra.
然后我们来到脐轮(Nabhi Chakra)
In Nabhi Chakra also we do not understand
在脐轮也是 我们不了解
that eating is not such an important thing.
吃其实不是这么重要的事
Doesn't matter if you don't eat your food today,
无所谓你们今天 有没有吃你们的食物
what does it matter?
这有什么要紧吗
It's very important, you know!
你们看 现在吃变得很重要
In Pune we had a Puja,
在浦那(Pune)我们举办崇拜
and we had Western children sitting there in the Puja,
我们有来自西方的孩子
and there were Indian children also.
也有来自于印度的孩子 坐在崇拜会场之中
As usual Puja is always late,
一如往常
but it was in the evening, Sankrant Puja.
崇拜总是很晚
So the children, Western children, got up at eight o'clock,
在晚上 所有孩子们 有来自西方的孩子
whether it was Puja or anything,
不管崇拜是否仍在进行或任何事
and all marched out for their dinner.
全部走去吃他们的晚餐
It looked very bad. Indians couldn't understand,
这看起来非常糟糕 印度人不能了解
how can that be?
这怎能够发生
But they had to have their dinner at eight.
他们要在八点吃晚餐
Supposing they don't eat their food at eight o'clock,
假如他们不能够在八点吃晚餐
what will happen, will they die?
会发生什么事呢 他们会死吗
So in a way, we restrict children also
因此 在某种程度上
that they, as if they are very grown up, matured people.
彷佛已是长大成熟的人 的态度去行事
We are so enamored by our children,
我们对我们的孩子如此沉迷
as if to get children is something great.
好像有孩子是很伟大的一件事
Anybody can have children, what's so great about it?
任何人都能有小孩 这有什么了不起
You have to look after your children. It's all right.
你们要去照顾你们的孩子 这没关系
But it doesn't mean that you should all the time
但这不表示你们整天 只去溺爱他们
worry about them, and nobody else.
担忧他们而不顾其他事情
So, if you have to enter into the limbic area
因此 如果你们要 进入脑的边缘系统
which is the Virata's place, which is the,
即是宇宙大我 （维罗陀Virata）之所在
I would say, from Visshuddhi to Hamsa
这就是我说的 从喉轮到明善轮
and then to your limbic area, into the Virata,
再从你们的边缘系统到维罗陀
then your interest must expand.
这时你们的兴趣会伸展
So the other discretion should be that:
另一种明辨力应该是
"Am I only thinking of my child?
我是否只想着我的孩子
Am I only thinking of my wife?
我是否只想着我的妻子
Am I only thinking about them,
我是否只想着他们
or I am worried about others' children also?
还是我也关心其他人的孩子
I'm thinking about others' children?"
我也想着其他人的孩子
I just tell you this because it's such a
我只告诉你这个
and you destroy your children also, by
你们也以这种没有明辨力的关心 来摧毁你们的孩子
Like we had a school in India,
像我们在印度有一所学校
and the children stayed in Pune. I had My Puja.
孩子们待在浦那（Pune） 参加为我举行的崇拜
I told them: "Don't bring children",
我告诉他们不要带孩子来
because I knew these children are Western children,
因为我知道这些孩子来自于西方
not easy, they can't bear anything.
他们不容易承受任何事情
But the children insisted,
但那些孩子坚持老师要带他们来
So the Puja was over as usual, very late,
崇拜一如以往很晚才结束
about I think eleven o'clock in the night,
我想大约是晚上十一点
and there was no transport,
那时没有任何交通工具
and that's why I said: "Don't bring them."
这就是我说别带他们来的原因
So they had to get some sort of a truck,
他们要乘搭某种卡车
because these days we were not getting petrol,
因为当时我们没有汽油
we had been having a very bad time.
当时我们的情况很艰辛
So they had to go on the truck.
他们要搭卡车
It reached there by about two o'clock.
约凌晨二点才到
Some of the fathers were staying in My house.
有些孩子们的父亲在我的房子休息
Next day they said: "Mother, our right heart is catching."
隔天他们说 母亲 我右心轮阻塞
I said: "What is that?"
我说 发生了什么事
"Such cruelty!"
这么残酷
I said: "What cruelty?"
我说 什么残酷
"The children reached at two o'clock in the school." So what?
孩子们凌晨二点才回到学校 那又如何
Right heart is catching!
右心轮阻塞
What attachments!
如此的执着于孩子
Your children, if they reach at two o'clock,
如果他们凌晨二点才抵达
what does it matter?
那又有什么关系
Why are you so much concerned about it?
为什么你们对这个如此关心
They are realized souls,
他们是自觉的灵
there is God who is looking after them.
神在照顾他们
Why are you so much worried about them?
为什么你们这么担心他们
Leave them alone.
不要管他们
They send them to India School.
送他们到印度学校
Then the mothers are sitting there.
然后孩子的母亲们坐在那儿
Teachers don't like it. No-one likes it.
老师们不喜欢这样 没有人喜欢这样
They have just gone there, mothers.
那些母亲们就去到学校
No school allows such nonsense.
没有一间学校会 允许这样的荒谬事情
But in Sahaja Yoga they think they have a right.
但是在霎哈嘉瑜伽他们认为 他们有权这样做
What right have they got? Have they paid for the school,
他们有什么权利 他们付钱盖这所学校吗
have they done anything for the school?
他们为这所学校做过些什么吗
What right have they got to go and sit in the school?
他们有什么权利到学校坐着不走
So the discretion should be, we
因此明辨是非的能力应该是
The first of the principles of Sahaja Yoga is fortitude.
霎哈嘉瑜伽的首要原则是坚毅
Sahaja Yoga is not meant for such dainty darlings.
霎哈嘉瑜伽不是给被宠坏的孩子
You have to be soldiers of Sahaja Yoga.
你们要成为霎哈嘉瑜伽的兵士
Your children have to be the soldiers of Sahaja Yoga,
你们的孩子要成为 霎哈嘉瑜伽的兵士
not the dainty darlings. It's not meant for them.
不是被宠坏的孩子 这不是他们所应得的
Though they are born realized,
虽然他们生来就得到自觉
you are ruining them by making them dainty darlings.
但你们藉由宠他们而毁灭他们
You have to rough it out. You have to make them sturdy.
你们要划分清楚 你们要让他们强健
You have to give them self-respect.
你们要给他们自尊
You have to give them dignity and a fortitude, forbearance.
你们要给他们尊严 坚毅和耐力
So this left Nabhi, right Nabhi,
在左脐轮 右脐轮
specially the left Nabhi, is a very big problem,
特别在左脐轮 是个很大的问题
where the woman has to be a Gruha Lakshmi
这里女士要成为 家户女神（Gruha Lakshmi）
and husband has not to be a Romeo, but a husband.
丈夫不是罗密欧 而是名副其实的丈夫
He has to see how his wife behaves.
他要看好他太太的言行举止
Correct her - that is his job, his duty.
纠正她 这是他的工作 他的责任
He should not shirk it.
他不应该逃避
Gruha Lakshmi is the woman who should know that
成为家户女神的女性应该要知道
she has the great responsibility
她身负开创伟大的 霎哈嘉瑜伽社会的重大责任
She's not an ordinary woman.
她不是平凡的女性
How many women got their realization before?
以前有多少女士得到自觉呢
But in Sahaja Yoga if you find the ladies,
但是在霎哈嘉瑜伽 如果你看女士
you hardly find very few who are really alert.
你很少能够找到一两位 真正有警觉的女士
Most of them are in trance condition.
她们大部分都在恍惚的状态
They don't know anything.
她们什么都不知道
They don't know anything. They don't know much of cooking,
她们不太会烹饪
you ask them anything, they don't know anything.
你问她们任何事情 她们什么都不知道
You talk to them, you feel as if
你跟她们说话
Nothing goes into their heads.
她们的脑袋记不住任何事情
Sometimes one feels, it's better I do it Myself, impossible.
有时候你会觉得 我干脆自己来算了
The alertness is gone,
真是令人难以忍受
because alertness that comes
警觉性的丧失
through your right side is wasted on nonsensical things.
是因为源自你们右脉的警觉 浪费在无意义的事情之上
Attention is wasted on nonsensical things, that's why
注意力浪费在无意义的事情之上
They should know each and everything.
她们应该要知道每一件事情
It's not so. They just live in the air,
但事实并非如此 她们总是活在虚空之中
somewhere hanging, you know.
在某处晃荡 你们是知道的
You don't know what to say to them,
你不知道要跟她们说什么
how to ask for anything.
如何向她们要求任何东西
How to explain anything to them is an impossible situation.
不可能去跟她们解释任何事
So that alertness has to be there
因此每位主妇都要具备警觉性
So we have Fatima at a young age.
我们有年轻的法蒂玛(Fatima)
She had these two sweet children
她两位可爱的孩子死于战争之中
What a brave woman,
多么勇敢的女人
the way she established the Shia system.
她建立了什叶派
Her husband also died,
她的丈夫也去世
and she did all that on her own.
她独自承担一切
Living behind the purdah, living behind the walls,
生活在重重围篱之中
she managed everything.
她承担了一切
We have had many such queens in our country.
在我们的国家中 有过许多这样的皇后
There was a seventeen-year-old widow,
以前有位十七岁的寡妇
who was the daughter-in-law of Shivaji;
她是希瓦吉（Shivaji）的儿媳
she fought with Aurangzeb and defeated him,
在我们的国家中 她与敌人战斗并打败了他
But if you do not have the alertness,
但是如果你失去了警觉
then you cannot be a Gruha Lakshmi,
那么你不能成为家户女神
you cannot be a good mother, you cannot be a good wife.
你不能成为好母亲 你不能成为好妻子
There's no slavery in it.
这不是件苦差事
They don't know even what pleases their husbands,
但她们甚至不知道什么 会让她们的先生喜悦
how to create peace in the family, what to say,
不知道如何在家中创造平安 该说些什么
when to say beautiful things and when to be strict.
何时该说些美丽的事情 以及何时该严格
All this discretion is not there.
所有的明辨力都已丧失
Either they are shrews or they are slaves.
她们不是成为泼妇 就是奴隶
So, Sahaja Yoga is meant for women who are alert,
霎哈嘉瑜伽是给那些有警觉性
who are wise, who know everything about life.
有智慧 知道关于生命的 一切的女士们
Even they don't know, where are the chakras on the feet.
但她们甚至不知道脚上 轮穴(charka)的分布情形
Look at your Mother. She's a woman. She knows so much.
看看你们的母亲 她是女性 她知道这么多
They don't know anything as to how
而那些女士们对于
Kundalini passes through these centers,
灵量(kundalini) 如何通过这些轮穴
what it does, what She is capable of.
祂的作用 以及祂可以成就的 事情都一无所知
But the Kundalini itself is the feminine Power.
灵量本身是母性的力量
She knows each and everything about you, about your child.
她知道关于你的一切事情 关于她孩子的一切事情
Many mothers don't know if the child is taking drugs,
许多母亲不知道孩子是否吸毒
or is behaving which way.
或是做了些什么
Except for spoiling or beating, there's nothing in between.
除了责打与溺爱 没有其他方式
With discretion, the mothers
借着明辨是非的能力,
That is My vision about them.
那是我对他们的期望
But with their indiscretion
但是 她们不能明辨是非
they can ruin these children completely.
使她们完全毁灭这些孩子
This is so important, that our Hamsa should be all right,
我们的明善轮良好是如此的重要
that we should be able to create a beautiful home,
使我们能够创造美丽的家
a peaceful home - not only for our family,
平安的家——不只为了我们的家人
but for all the other Sahaja Yogis who come to our house.
也为了所有其他来到我们家里的 霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者
I don't know how it has come into the
我不知道这想法 如何进入印度女性的脑中
I don't know how,
我不知道如何做到
but if you have to please them you have to just say:
但如果你想要让她们高兴 你只要这么说
"Sister-in-law, will you cook this for me tomorrow?"
好姊妹 妳愿意明天 为我煮这道菜吗
Or if you say: "I am coming for dinner or lunch",
或者如果你说 我想来吃晚餐或午餐
that's the best. They are very much pleased.
那是最好不过 她们会非常非常高兴
"Oh!" Just they're thinking:
啊 她们将会马上开始想
"Oh, what am I going to cook, what does he like?"
我要煮些什么 他喜欢吃什么
They know about each and every person, what he likes.
她们知道每个人喜欢什么
It's not slavishness.
这不是件苦差事
If you want to please someone it's not slavishness.
如果你想要让某个人高兴 那不是件苦差事
The whole nature is there to please us.
整个大自然都在取悦我们
Is it the slavish thing to do?
这是件苦差事吗
But the another side of a woman is she's a Raja Lakshmi,
女士的另一方面是她是 罗什拉希什米（Raja Lakshmi）
and the man who is the king.
而男士是国王
The discretion at that point is: are you dignified or not?
在这里的明辨力是 你有尊严吗
We went to Japan once,
我们曾到访日本
and they were treating us with great respect,
他们非常地礼遇我们
even in a village.
甚至在村庄也是这样
First we entered a shop because it was raining,
有一次我们因为下雨 而走进一家店铺
so the villagers actually bowed to us.
村民认真地对我们鞠躬
We didn't understand what's happening.
我们不知道发生了什么事
And they, they gave us presents.
他们还送礼物给我们
So we asked ultimately, then, the interpreter:
我们问翻译人员
"Why are they so humble before us?"
为什么他们在我们面前如此谦卑
They said: "Because you belong to royal family."
他们说 因为你们是皇室成员
I said: "No, we don't belong to royal family."
我说 不 我们不是皇室成员
How would they know? No."
他们怎么知道呢 不是
Because your hair are neat,
因为你们的头发干净整齐
your daughters' hair are neat and shiny.
你们的女儿们头发整洁明亮
And you don't go to hairdressers." that was it!
你们不去找理发师 那么
"Is this a sign, is this a sign of royal family?"
我说 这是个象征吗 这是皇室的象征吗
Yes, that's how the royal family is.
是的 皇室就是如此
They don't put their head into the hands of somebody else."
他们不把头交到别人的手中
We were amazed. Imagine the Japanese thinking like that!
你们会很惊讶 想象一下日本人的想法
So the discretion is
因此这明辨力是妳要像皇后
and the husband has to be like a king.
而丈夫要像国王
But not like the king who killed his seven wives,
但不是像那杀了七位妻子的国王
but like a king who respects his wife.
而是尊敬妻子的国王
If you cannot respect your wife,
如果你不能尊重妻子
you cannot be a Sahaja Yogi.
你就不是霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者
Respect is different from being romantically in love.
尊重与浪漫地坠入爱河不同
I think that you don't respect.
我想这样的话你不会去尊重
To respect your wife is a very important thing in Sahaja Yoga.
在霎哈嘉瑜伽中 尊敬你的妻子是非常重要的事
For this, I would say the Indians are not so good,
就这点 我得说 印度人表现的不太好
but also I know some of the Western people
但我也知道有些西方人也十分荒谬
Your dignity is reduced if you cannot respect your wife.
如果你不能尊敬妻子 你的尊严会降低
Indians, especially in the North India, not in the South,
印度人 特别是北印度而不是南部
they lack this, to respect their wives.
他们不去尊重妻子
Also, they lack the discretion that a wife,
他们缺乏这明辨力
if she is not respected,
如果妻子不被尊重
the children will not be respectful to her
孩子们将不会尊重她
and she is in charge of the children.
而她需要管教孩子
But the most indiscreet thing about Nabhi
关于脐轮最缺乏明辨力的事情
is that you don't listen to your Guru.
是你们不听从你们的导师
Hundred times you tell something to Sahaja Yogis,
即使对霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者说数百次
but still they will not listen to Me.
他们还是不听我的话
Still, they will do as the fashion tells them
他们还是会跟随潮流
or the norms that they have.
或他们既有的超我去做事情
Listening to your Guru, as they say, as if
听从你们的导师
Whatever is said is to be accepted as a great blessing,
无论我说了什么
as a great correction and is to be followed,
极大的改正去接受 并且去遵行
not to be just left out as it is.
而不是听听就算了
As you know, your Mother is your Guru
你们知道 你们的母亲是你们的导师
and She's your Mother. Also She's Mahamaya.
她也是你们的母亲 她也是摩耶幻相
Also She's Adi Shakti. And She's so gentle
她也是太初之母 她是如此温柔
and She's so kind.
如此仁慈
She says some things to you to correct you.
她对你们说话是为了要改正你们
So many lectures I've given,
这么多的演讲中
of telling you what is important.
我告诉你们什么是重要的
But you should open your heart and surrender it
但是你们应该要打开心扉
otherwise there is no way out, I'm sorry to say.
要不然没有其他方法 我很抱歉要这么说
I do not like anybody surrendering to Me
我不喜欢任何人跪在我面前
or touching My Feet or falling at Me.
碰触我的脚 向我拜倒
I, I, I don't understand that. I mean,
我不了解这些
I'm not conscious of it, not aware of it.
我的意思是我没有感觉到这些 没有察觉到这些
It makes no difference to Me. Even when you sing My Jai,
对我而言并无分别
I think that you are singing some Mataji Nirmala Devi's Jai,
我想你们在对某个叫 锡吕․玛塔吉․涅玛拉․德维的人 高唱万岁
in the third person,
以第三者的角度
and sometimes I'm afraid I might say "Jai" with you.
有时我恐怕也会 跟你们一起高呼万岁
When you are singing "Swagata Agat"
当你们唱欢迎歌（Swagatam）
I always think there's some Mataji Nirmala Devi
我总是认为他们在对某个叫
"Swagat" song they are singing somebody else.
唱欢迎歌 另一个人
But for your goodness, for your ascent
但是为了你们的好处
you have not come here just to waste your time,
你们不是来这里浪费时间
but to ascend, and for that it is important
而是为了要升进
But I never say a thing which will be uncomfortable for you.
我从未说任何 会让你们不舒服的事
I never say: "You don't take your food"
我从未说你们不要吃东西
or "Don't drink water" - nothing of the kind.
不要喝水——从未说过这样的话
But, out of laziness, people just don't do many things;
但是 出于懒惰 很多事人们就是不去做
or, if not laziness, then just they do not know how
如果不是懒惰
So the discretion is that Guru is Parabrahma
因此要能明辨 导师就是大梵（Parabrahma）
any guru, Satguru.
任何存在的真正导师(Sat Guru)
But what about the Parabrahma Itself, which is your Guru?
但若大梵本身就是你们的导师呢
I do not say things as hearty as the gurus used to do it.
我不像其他导师一样习惯于 热切地阐述事情
I mean, if you read about them you'll be shocked.
我的意思是 如果你们读他们的书 你们将会很震惊
But whatever I say, every word, you must note,
但是 无论我说了些什么
and for the benevolence of the whole world.
为了全世界的福祉
And, by not obeying Me in that,
若不去遵从它们
you are not only spoiling your own chances,
你们不仅仅毁掉了 你们自己的机会
but the chances of the whole world.
也毁掉了全世界的机会
So you understand how important it is
所以你们要了解 如果你们是门徒
if you are the disciple, if you are blessed by your Guru.
如果你们被你们的导师所祝福 这是如何的重要
All these things are written about them,
这一切都有书籍记载
but I say not only that you are My disciples,
但我说你们不仅是我的门徒
but you have got your realization, you are Sahaja Yogis.
你们还得到你们的自觉 你们是霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者
You got all the powers. You know each and everything.
你们有所有的力量 你们知道每一件事情
You are so special people.
你们是如此特别的人们
For such people there should not be any difference of opinion,
对我们这样的人而言 不应该有任何不同的意见
because you know the same thing all the time,
因为你们无时无刻都是同一的
so there cannot be any fight,
因此不能有任何争吵
there cannot be any quarrel,
不能有任何口角
there cannot be any argument.
不能有任何争辩
But the discretion should be that our Guru is a Mother.
明辨力应该是 我们的导师是位母亲
She's very mild. She's very gentle.
她非常温和 她非常温柔
She's very kind. I know that.
她非常仁慈 我知道
One day, My brother told Me,
有一天我弟弟对我说
that: "What sort of a Guru You are?
妳是怎样的一位导师
When my guru was teaching me tabla,
我的老师教我打 塔布拉鼓（tabla）的时候
he used to break the tampura on my head,
他会把坦布拉琴（tampura） 砸在我头上
and even one percussion I would make wrong,
我只要打错一拍
he would bring his hammer:
他会带着他的锤子说
'And now I'm going to break your nails!'
现在我要打断你的指甲
I said: "There's no need to do all this.
我说 不需要这么做
Not necessary in Sahaja Yoga,
在霎哈嘉瑜伽中不需要
because they are self-disciplined."
因为他们会自律
So there has to be the self-disciplination,
因此你们在明善轮 要有所说的自律
as you can so call it, on the Hamsa Chakra,
明善轮是那个
which is the one which knows what is right, what is wrong,
知道什么是对 什么是错的轮穴
through which we work it out; whatever is the right
藉由它我们达成自律 我们只做对的事情
Then comes the Heart Chakra.
接下来是心轮
We talk of love. We talk of this. We talk of that.
我们谈论爱 我们说这个 我们说那个
I mean, so much of talk of love in the West,
在西方有这么多关于爱的言谈
which is never in India.
这在印度从未发生过
But there isn't any love.
但是却没有任何爱
It is such a love for money, love for possessions,
这是对金钱的爱 对地位的爱
but there is no pure love, Nirvaj. There's no love like that.
但却没有纯洁的爱 没有爱
So the discretion between your family
所以要清楚地分辨你的家庭 与别人的家庭
you will know that you are doing something wrong.
你会知道你正在做错事
This is more in India than here, abroad.
这在印度比在国外要多
That there is no discretion, about the Family
关于家庭 人们没有判断力
like people are coming to see me
像人们来拜访我
so a foreign couple will stay back.
一对夫妻留下后
One by one they'll come. All right, couples are all right.
其他人一个接一个地来 好吧 夫妻一起没有关系
But they'll not bring their uncles, aunties,
但是他们不能带他们的舅舅们 阿姨们
their aunties' parents, their parents, and then
他们阿姨的父母 他们的父母
Together they will come in one line.
成群结队 从来不排队
They will always be grouped together.
他们总是会聚成一团
All of them will be on My head. I have seen.
他们全部的人都会排聚在一起 我曾见过
There's no discretion there,
这里缺乏明辨出
that we are individuals as far as Mother is concerned.
对母亲而言 我们都是个别的 的能力
She is our Mother. She's our Guru
她是我们的母亲 她是我们的导师
and we have to face Her individually,
我们必须单独地面对她
not to take all this paraphernalia with us:
而不是带着这么多的羁绊
all our relations, my brothers or my sisters or my this and that.
我们所有的关系 我的兄弟 我的姊妹 我的这个 那个
So the discretion as far as the guru is concerned,
对于导师而言
is an extremely important thing in Sahaja Yoga.
在霎哈嘉瑜伽中这明辨力 非常重要
It is.. You want Me to explain to you how
你们要我向你们解释
the gravity acts through Nabhi. No doubt.
重力（gravity） 如何透过脐轮作用
But through your Heart Chakra, if you gravitate at people,
但是经由你们的心轮 如果你们被人们
or sort of what you call, the charisma of a person
或被你们所称的个人领袖魅力
or some sort of a nonsense, or the charmingness of a person,
个人某些无意义的性质 或魅力所吸引
that means you're attracted towards something
这表示你们被某些极度肤浅的事情
So, the discretion at the Heart
因此 在心轮中的明辨力
is to have a relationship which is so detached
是去拥有无执着的关系
that you nourish everything, every part of your family.
使你可以去滋养一切事物 滋养你们家庭的每一部分
Now somebody's attached to the husband,
现在有人执着于丈夫
somebody's attached to children,
有人执着于孩子
somebody's attached to the dogs,
有人执着于狗
somebody's attached to the, only to the plants.
有人只关心植物
It's very indiscreet.
非常没有明辨力
You should be attached to everything the same, same way.
你们应该要同样地对待一切事物
I would say that you should be so detached
我应该这么说 你们应该要如此地无执着
that you are attached to everyone equally.
使你们同样地对待每个人
Detachment doesn't mean that you wear dresses scantily.
无执着不表示 你们穿裙子或是吝啬
It doesn't mean that. It's a wrong idea.
不是这个意思 这是错误的观念
Detachment means that you watch everything,
无执着的意思是你们观看一切
and you do not get involved with anyone.
而不涉入任何事之中
You are out of it, and you are seeing everything,
你们在它之外 你们看见一切
watching it, you're a witness.
观看它 你是静观者
This sort of love if you have for anyone,
这是一种爱 如果你对任何人都具备这份爱
you will be blessed by that personality very much more.
你们会被这样的人格 更为深厚地祝福
So now the discretion of the Vishuddhi
喉轮的明辨力
is another very important thing.
也是另一件非常重要的事
The other day somebody came, and his right hand was frozen.
某一天有人到来 她的右手僵硬
I asked him: "What do you do?" He says:
我问她 你做什么工作
I said: "You take to Sahaja Yoga,
我说 你来到霎哈嘉瑜伽
and before typing you just say 'Namaskar' to that
在打字前你只要说 敬拜（Namaskar）
work that you have to do, just like that,
开始工作时你只要这么做
and then you start doing the work,
然后你开始工作
as if you are not doing it.
彷佛你没有在做事似的
You are just doing it, typing,
你只是去做——打字
you are just typing, that's all. You are not doing it,
你只是在打字 如此而已 你没有在做事
you are not doing anything
你没有做任何事
Some people say, "Mother, You travel so much." I never travel.
有些人说 母亲 您这么频繁地旅行 我从未旅行
I'm sitting or I'm walking. Where do I travel?
我坐着或走着 我那来的旅行
It's the plane that travels, I'm just sitting in the plane.
是飞机在旅行 我只是坐在飞机上
I never travel like a Superman. I'm sitting very nicely.
我从未像超人般的飞行 我舒舒服服地坐着
Where do I travel? If I start thinking: "I travel very much,
我旅行到哪里 如果我开始想 我频繁地旅行
I do this work, I do that work",
我做了这个工作 做了那个工作
somebody would say: "Mother, you do so much work."
有人会说 母亲 您做了这么多工作
I mean I don't do anything. I tell you, really,
我的意思是 我没有做任何事 我告诉你们 真的
I don't do anything. Now I'm speaking. All right.
我没有做任何事
So, just I'm speaking, that's all;
我只是在讲话 只是这样而已
and this speech also I'm not doing it.
这场演讲也是 我没有做事
It's just coming out, like a radio.
它只是如同收音机 一般地播放出来
Would you say that the radio is doing any work?
你们会说收音机做了任何工作吗
It's just a radio.
它只是台收音机
Actually, I don't do anything whatsoever.
实际上 我完全没有做任何工作
So when I'm not doing anything, why should I feel tired?
所以当我没有做任何事的时候 我怎会感觉疲累呢
Why should I wear out? So this feeling of:
我怎会筋疲力竭
is responsible for creating your problems of ego within you.
在你的内在为你创造了 自我的问题
So, to use the discretion over this ego,
因此 要用明辨是非的能力 驾驭自我
to put it down in its proper place,
好把它降回合适的地方
are these strands of Ida and Pingala
这些位于左脉与右脉顶部的力量 把它们降下来
And it's like a brake and an accelerator.
这就像是煞车与加速器
So, if somebody has too much of ego
因此 如果某人太过自我
then the discretion, see, is missing from that person.
那么明辨力 你们看 会从这人身上消失
He does something, thinks: "I have done this,
他做了一些事情 想着 我做了这个
I have done that"; as they say, Humpty Dumpty sort.
我做了那个
And then he suddenly finds that's finished.
然后他突然发现什么都结束了
"I was very stupid to have such a, such an ego."
我有这样的自我真是太愚蠢了
So, what does he say? "All right, Mother, You do help me.
所以他应该说什么呢 好 母亲 您来为我做
You work it out." Finished. It's done.
您来成就它 就这样结束 这事就成了
Of course I don't do anything, nor you do anything.
当然 我没有做任何事 你们也没有做任何事
If you just say, "Mother, please do this for me", it's done.
如果你们这么说 母亲 请为我做这件事
If you say, "Mother, come in my head",
如果你们说 母亲 来到我的头脑之中
I come in your head;
我就来到你们的脑中
"Come in my eyes", I come in your eyes.
来到我的眼中 我来到你们的眼中
Say what you like, I don't do anything at all.
你想要什么就说什么 我没有做任何事
Neither you do anything. It just works!
你也没有做任何事 它就是成就了
Somebody else is doing - all right?
让别的人在做 好吗
Need not bother about that. Somebody's doing it,
不需要担忧 有别的人在做
but as long as I am not doing it, I am relaxed and
只要我没有在做 我轻松
I am not worried. I am not upset.
而且不担心 我不会沮丧
So Visshuddhi is a very, very important center,
喉轮是非常 非常重要的中心
and for you Americans, especially, American Sahaja Yogis,
对于你们美国人 尤其是美国的霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者
you have to know that to be in the Visshuddhi
你们要了解 位于喉轮表示你们掌握一切
Not doing anything, but in charge.
没有做任何事 但是掌握一切
Like these two hands are there,
像这两只手在这里
and you should know that it's the Visshuddhi Chakra
你们要知道喉轮
which controls the two most important chakras,
是在管理两个最重要的轮穴
are Lalita Chakra and Shri Chakra. Just think about it.
月轮与日轮 只要想想这点
How important is Visshuddhi?
喉轮多么重要
How important is America? Just think of it.
美国多么重要 只要想想这点
But nobody's aware of it. America means Las Vegas,
但是没有人察觉到这点 美国只意味着拉斯韦加斯
then all these horrible beaches
然后是所有可怕的海滩
horrible, horrible, horrible!
可怕的 可怕的 可怕的
Nobody knows what is America is,
没有人知道美国是什么
what does it mean to be in America,
身处在美国的意义是什么
what's our responsibility.
我们的责任是什么
All this comes to you when you allow your
当你们允许你们的灵量 上升到这里
Kundalini to be up there,
你们会拥有这一切
so you're absolutely detached,
你们会绝对地无执着
you're connected with the mains, like this one,
你们像这机器一样连接到主机
and the whole work is done by the mains.
全部的工作都由主机所完成
You don't have to do anything.
你们什么都不必做
So when you are detached of doing anything,
你们对于做任何事情
of appreciating anything or debasing anything,
或欣赏任何事情 或贬低任何事情
or judging anything, when you are not at all
或评断任何事情都不执着
that means you are absolutely detached
表示你们在真实世界中 绝对地无执着
So this works up to the Agnya Chakra.
这作用上升至额轮
We can say that all these
我们可以说
they are built in, they are spontaneous,
它们是与生俱来的 它们是自然而然的
and you have to just allow them to grow,
你们所要的只是允许它们成长
by meditating, by watching yourself every minute,
藉由静坐 藉由每分每秒地 观察你们自己
every second, whether are you enjoying yourself or not?
看看你们是不是在享受自己
So the whole of discretion rests on one point:
因此整个明辨是非的能力 包含在这一点之中
how far you are enjoying Sahaja Yoga. What a nice thing!
你们能多么享受霎哈嘉瑜伽 它是多么的美好
Like yesterday, I was meeting every sort of a person,
像昨天 我跟每个不同的人会面
and some, some of them felt I was exerting too much Myself.
有人认为我太过于勉强自己
No, no, no, no, not at all! I was enjoying all of them.
不是这样的 不 不 不 一点儿都不会
Sahaja Yoga is a very big joker - very big joker.
有个非常爱玩笑的人 非常爱开玩笑的人
Say a person comes up to you, you talk to that person.
假如一个人来到你跟前 你就同这个人说话
It's a drama behind every individual
每个人背后都有一出戏
and you discover what a drama this individual was.
你会发现这人有的 是怎样的一出戏
No need to go to any theatre or any film!
不需要去任何戏院或看任何电影
Every personality is a drama. Very enjoyable
每个人格都是一出戏 这非常令人享受
if you just want to see the drama
如果你只想去看戏
and if you just know that, oh, you have to watch the drama!
如果你只知道 噢 你要看这出戏
You have to see it.
你们要知道这个
Only painful part is, that as a guru,
唯一痛苦的地方是 身为导师
I have to tell them this is not good, that is not good.
我必须要指出这个不好 那个不好
That's the only painful thing.
这是唯一痛苦的事
I wish I could have avoided it somehow, but it's not possible.
我希望我能有法子不去这样做 但这是不可能的
Because from the darkness to the sunlight you have to come out,
因为你们要从黑暗走向光明
and you're holding My hand so I have to tell you
你们握着我的手 我必须告诉你们要小心
and both the sides you can fall off into Ida and Pingala.
你可能会从两边跌落到 左脉与右脉之中
So hold My hand tightly, we have to go further. Further. Further
紧紧握住我的手 我们要走得 更远 更远 更远
Don't look this side, that side. That's all.
不要看这边 那边 这样就好
And this is what it is when you have discretion
这就是当你们有明辨力
to put your hand into the hands of your Guru.
把你们的手放在导师的手中 所会发生的事情
Then you don't do anything. You just watch everyone,
之后你们不做任何事 你们只是静观每个人
see everyone and only thing you do is to enjoy.
观看每个人 你们只是去享受
Whether you do it or not is not the point,
你们做与不做并不是重点
but you are in the state of enjoyment,
你们在享受的境界之中
completely in the state of enjoyment.
完全在享受的境界中
And that is the state we have to achieve,
这就是我们所要达到的境界
and should become that state as our own being.
我们自己应该要成为这境界
Up to Hamsa Chakra you have come
你们已经到达明善轮
and the Kundalini is now ready to open,
灵量现在已准备好 并要非常良好地开启
She knows you very well,
她清清楚楚地知道你们
and the Kundalini knows that you can now
灵量知道你们现在可以
pass through Agnya.
通过额轮
Your attention can pass through Agnya
你们的注意力可以通过额轮
because you have discretion.
因为你们有明辨是非的能力
You've cleared out yourself of all these loads and things,
你们把自己从这么多负荷 俗务之中清理出来
and you can now pass through this Agnya.
现在你们可以通过额轮了
So before realization, those people who have had
因此 在得到自觉之前 那些有明辨是非能力的人
They're solid people.
他们是稳固的人
Or, those who are weak again and again fall and rise,
至于那些一次又一次降下又上升
fall and rise, fall and rise. They catch again and again.
降下又上升 降下又上升的人们 他们一次又一次地阻塞
So the discretion, at that time,
在这时刻的明辨能力
is to know that you are here for your ascent
是要去了解你们在此只是为了升进
and for nothing else.
而不为其他
And that has to work spontaneously
这升进只能藉由发现喜悦
but they told Me that: "Mother, we have to do this,
但是他们跟我说 母亲 我们要做这个
we have to do that. What to do? This and that."
我们要做那个 怎么办才好 这个跟那个
Just leave it at that point. Just leave it,
你们只要把它放下 只要放下它
and everything will work out. You are not doing anything.
然后一切都会成就 你们没有做任何事
You are not really doing anything.
你们没有真的做任何事
It's this all-pervading Power, which is so efficient,
是无所不在的生命能量 为你们做这一切
is doing everything for you.
它是如此有效率
There is one point which
这里有一点
I wanted to tell you about the Ashram life.
我想跟你们说在集体静室的 生活（Ashram life）
We have ashrams and ashrams and ashrams everywhere.
我们称为集体静室 到处是静室 静室 静室
Ashram is a small world.
静室只是个名称
It is a symbol of an ideal world of the enlightened people.
觉醒的人的理想世界的象征
It's not that only those who are having no house:
而不是为了没房子住的人
"All right, you have no house? Come along!
好吧 你没有房子 来吧
Because you can pay the rent!"
因为你付不起房租
It's meant for people who are of that quality.
静室是为了有质素的人而设
So now in the ashram one has to realize
在集体静室中 你们要知道
that you are under complete observation.
自己在全面的观察之中
So you have to be alert. Somebody's watching you.
你们必须要警觉 人们在观察你们
Now you have come in the camera.
现在你们已经来到镜头底下
You are now in the ashram.
你们现在在静室中
So let's start from the very beginning, as I said,
让我们如同我之前所说 从最根本开始
in an ashram, as far as the Mooladhara is concerned.
以根轮来说 在静室中应该要如何
That part I think most of you have worked out,
我想你们大部分人都已经做到
that you should keep an extremely clean atmosphere.
你们应该要保持极度洁凈的氛围
But I have seen some mad people, even in the ashram,
但是我见过有些疯子 甚至在静室中
start behaving in a manner
他们的言行举止
that doesn't show that they are Ashramites.
不像是个住在静室的人
Their behavior is so funny towards sex sometimes
他们对性的举止滑稽
that I just don't understand.
有时我其实不能够理解
The relationship between the husband and wife also:
夫妻之间的关系也是
either they fight with their fists or their legs or feet,
他们不是拳打脚踢 大打出手
or otherwise they're absolutely docile
就是绝对地顺从
and given up each other.
互相放弃
It is such a misunderstanding we have,
明善轮没有得到觉醒时
without Hamsa Chakra being enlightened,
我们会有这么大的误解
that we take to things which were so dangerous for us,
使我们接受那些对我们 以及长久以来
for our society a long time back, just for granted,
对我们社会非常危险的事情 将它们视为理所当然
and we start doing the same thing.
并开始做同样的事情
If not to go down to that level,
虽然我们没有落到这种地步
but we try to keep company with such people,
但我们就尝试与这些人为伍
we try to so-called "help" them, whatever we try to do
我们尝试去所谓 帮助 他们
We are so indiscreet
我们是如此没有明辨是非的能力
that whatever we try to do for others, anything:
以致于无论我们尝试 为别人做些什么 任何事情
either there is some sort of a passion
不是出于某种热情
or a obsession or some sort of a gain or whatever it is,
就是出于执迷 或是想获得 某种东西 或是任何东西
then it is indiscreet, absolutely indiscreet.
这缺乏明辨是非的能力 是绝对没有明辨是非的能力
Because you don't do anything, it just flows,
你们没有做任何事 它只是流动
goes to everyone.
经过每一个人
So, in the ashram the life should be very pure.
在集体静室中 生活应该要非常纯洁
Relationship should, should be very pure,
关系应该要非常纯洁
there should be respect of the elders.
你们应该要尊敬长辈
will have a right Visshuddhi problem, always.
那些不能尊敬长辈的人 总是有右喉轮的问题
They must know how to respect their elders,
他们必须知道如何去尊敬长辈
and a proper respect of the representative of your Guru.
如何对你们导师的代表 有适当的尊敬
The other chakras are to be seen in the same manner.
其他的轮穴也要用 同样的方式去查看
In an ashram try to have things which are spontaneous.
在集体静室中 尝试用自然的东西
Not to have something artificial
而不是人工的东西
or some things your Guru won't like.
或是你们导师不会喜欢的东西
Like, I don't want to see there some sort of funny
像我不想看某些滑稽的图画
stupid kind of an emblem.
或愚蠢象征的东西
In a household that is Sahaj it should be felt by anybody
霎哈嘉的居室应该 要让任何到来的人觉得
clean, neat, tidy.
干净整齐 井然有序 有条不紊
And also, ashram should be a place of peace
同时静室应该充满平安
and happiness and joy.
快乐与喜悦的地方
If somebody comes to that ashram he should feel:
如果有人来到静室 他应该会觉得
"What a place I have found!
我找到一个多么好的地方
What a nice place it is! I wish I could also come here."
这地方真好 我希望能来这里
It's only your discretion that works it out,
只有你们的明辨力 能成就这样的事
that whatever you create, whatever you do is for the best.
无论你们创造些什么 无论你们在做什么 都是最好的
Now what do I do? You bring some water to Me,
现在我在做什么 你们给我一些水
I just put My hand. I do not vibrate.
我只是把我的手放进去 我没有传送生命能量
I do not do anything to vibrate, or just put My hand.
我没有做任何事去向它传送 生命能量——我只是把我的手放进去
Finished, it's vibrated.
当我做完了 它就有生命能量
Now why should I take any credit for it?
我为何要为这样的事获得任何赞赏
Just vibrated. Finished!
只是有了生命能量 完成了
Do I do anything? Anything else have you seen?
我没有做任何事 我什么也没做
In the same way,
同样地
when you are doing something you just think that:
当你们做某件事 你们只要想
I'm not doing anything. It's just this hand put there.
我没有做任何事 只是把手放在那里
If there is some red on my hand the water will become red.
如果我手上有些红色颜料 水就会变成红色
So what did I do? Nothing! Nothing.
所以我做了些什么呢 什么也没有 什么也没有
Now there are vibrations in my hand.
现在我手上有生命能量
You have put it in the water, it has been vibrated. So what?
如果我把它放在水中 水就会有生命能量 那又如何呢
Now in the ashram I have seen people are not alert at all.
在集体静室 我发现人们一点警觉性也没有
Now there's a telephone call comes in.
有人打电话来
It gets lost, or there's no communication.
没有人接听 没有人传达
One person doesn't tell another person
最糟糕的是——不去告诉别人
what is the telephone that has come.
在响的是那支电话
But even in the household we have to be careful and alert.
即使在家中我们也要小心谨慎
Like you put a paper there
你们可放些纸张
or some sort of a notebook
或笔记本在那儿
where you should write down today, whose telephones came.
好让你们可以写下 今天接到给谁的电话
Write it in, one after another.
让那人可以回电
It's one of the examples I'm just giving you,
我刚举个例子给你们
how you have to be alert about that.
关于如何对事情有所警觉
Now if you are cooking
例如你们烹饪
you should know how many people are going to eat.
你们应该要知道有多少人会吃
There are going to be, say, ten people,
比如说有十个人要吃
then the food will be cooked only for two.
你们只准备给二个人的食物
But if there are two persons,
如果有二个人
then the food will be cooked for ten people!
你们会煮给十个人吃的食物
And then the food is thrown out, because after all..
然后把食物丢掉 因为终究要丢掉
But this is absolutely absurd!
这是绝对荒谬的事情
I must tell you a story of Mahatma Gandhi.
我必须告诉你们甘地的一个故事
I was in his ashram. I was quite young at the time,
当时我在他的静室中 当时我还很年轻
but that is on My.. very much recorded.
但我记得大部分的事情
So he wanted everybody to stay for dinner - lunch.
他想要每个人留下来吃晚餐 午餐
They said: But we are going there. It's all right,
他们说 但我们要到那里 没关系
you can have your lunch with me;
你们可以跟我一起用午餐
and they were having a conference.
他们在开会
All the big johnnies were sitting there.
所有壮汉都在
So he got up, and he had the keys in his
他起身 他的秘书带给他钥匙
Came out, with his key he opened the storeroom and got
他用钥匙打开储藏室
like one person would get only one "chataque",
一个人应该只拿到一份
It was all measured, brought out, for cooking.
一切都量好才拿出来
So all these people were there. "Molanar sahib" said:
这些人全在那儿
to stand there with the keys, to take out everything.
拿钥匙开门 拿出每件东西
We - you have wasted so much your time for us.
您为我们浪费了太多时间
He said: What, wasted?
他说 什么 浪费
Yes, for this you had to stand there, and take out the food.
是的 为了这个 您要站在那里拿出食物
He said: Do you know, this is the blood of my countrymen.
他说 你们不知道这 是我国民的血液
There are so many people starving in this world,
有这么多人在世界各地挨饿
and if you throw food like that, I assure you,
如果你们把食物丢掉
You cannot insult food like that, but you have to be alert.
你们不能那样地侮辱食物 你们要有警觉
You go to an ashram, I've seen in Australia,
你去到静室——我曾在澳洲看过
everywhere it's on, you just go and ask them, all right:
每个地方都发生这样的事 你只要去问他们
No.
没有
Then what oil you have?
那你们有什么油
They said: "What oil?" Only going on like this.
什么油 就像这样
What is this? Where you have, what oil you have got?
这是什么 你们有些什么油
No-one knows what oil they have got.
没有人知道他们有什么油
They don't know. They don't read what oils they have got.
他们不知道 他们不去看看他们有什么油
So somebody brings an oil bottle.
有人把油罐拿来
I read it: "Castor oil."
我一看 蓖麻油
"Castor oil?" "Yes, what else?"
蓖麻油 是的 是这些罐子
I said: "Do you know for what castor oil is used?"
我说 你们知道蓖麻油 是拿来做什么用的吗
"No, Mother." "Do you cook in this oil?" "I don't know."
不知道 母亲 你们用这油来烹饪吗 我不知道
From where are you coming? Lunatic asylum, or what?
你们究竟是从哪里来的 精神病院吗
There is no alertness, is the point.
在这方面没有警觉
So, you have to get up at four o'clock, four-thirty.
所以 你们要在四点起床 四点半
I don't say you have to do it,
我不会说你们要这么做
but discipline yourself because
但你们要训练自己
that's the time you get the alertness,
因为这是你们得到警觉的时间
the first shooting of the rays of the sun gives you that.
清晨第一道曙光会给予你警觉
You'll always see Me early in the morning awake.
你们总是看见我早上很早就醒来
Not that I need that, but for your sake I get up.
不是我需要如此 我是为了你们起床
You can sleep later on, but that time you just get up.
你们之后可以睡 但是你们要在那时起床
First rays - sun comes much later, the rays come first.
第一道曙光——太阳 要更晚才会升起 曙光先至
That gives you alertness. Then you have your bath,
这给予你警觉 然后你们沐浴
do your Pujas. You are ready.
做崇拜 你们会准备好
By six o'clock you are ready and alert.
在早上六点的时候你们 会警觉并将一切准备就绪
But the alertness should be about everything.
对每件事应该有这警觉性
Now supposing I ask: "Where did you buy this?"
现在假如我问 你们从哪里买到这个
This should never be answered for anything.
关于任何物品这问题 都不会有答案
"Where do you get this made?"
这是哪里制的
I know everything, if you ask Me.
如果你问的话 我知道每一件事情
I may not know about this but I will find out
我也许不知道这个
Alertness about things, what we have,
对事物要有警觉 我们有些什么
what is in the ashram, are we keeping it clean or not,
静室有些什么东西 我们有没有保持干净
or we're lousy people, absolutely lousy,
还是我们是差劲的人 绝对差劲的人
don't know anything. Is a big fashion to say:
什么都不知道 现在很流行说
"I don't know." I'm not asking absurd question like:
我不知道 我不是在问荒谬的问题
"How many hair do you have in your head?",
像是 你头上有几根头发
or "How many stars there are?" A simple thing if I say:
或是 天上有几颗星星 很简单的事情
Same with the men I have seen.
同样我看过一些男士
It's not with the women, but men, also,
不是女士 而是男士
do not have that alertness that they should have.
他们没有应有的警觉
There's no communication among themselves.
我们之中没有沟通
They have more alertness because they are right-sided,
他们应有较多的警觉 因为他们倾向右脉
but they have no alertness about the feelings of others.
但是他们对于其他人的感受 就没有警觉
Like, there's a husband who is very rude to his wife,
像有位丈夫非常无礼地 对待他的太太
always insults her.
总是侮辱她
The alertness of the man should be in the ashram,
男士在静室应有的警觉是
is to shave off his head and also shave off his moustaches,
要梳理头发 刮胡子
and ask him just to go about with the pyjama.
或叫他别只穿长衣到处走动
Or even then he misbehaves,
如果是那样找个驴子让他坐上去吧
Even then if he misbehaves, then tell him:
即使如此 如果他行为不端庄 那么告诉他
"No water available for you, do what you like."
你今天没水了 你喜欢做什么就去做吧
Such punishment should be given to a man who misbehaves,
这样的处罚应该要给 行为不端的男士
who has no emotional feelings towards his wife,
对妻子无情的男士
who ill-treats. Or somebody who is very romantic,
或恶劣地对待妻子的男士 或有些人非常浪漫
also you should make fun of that person.
对这样的人你也可取笑他们
This is the alertness of men, is very important to see.
这是男士要有的警觉 非常重要
Also they should be alert as to how the money is spent.
他们也要对钱如何花掉而警觉
You know very well how they have made money
你们要非常清楚他们如何在 圣地亚哥的静室用我来赚钱
Nobody bothered even to find out, what's happening to this.
没有人在意 甚至没人想知道发生了什么事
They're paying their rent - finished!
他们付房租——罢了
Where are they spending? What are they doing about it?
他们把钱花在哪里 他们用这些钱做了什么
Nobody knows about it.
没有人知道
I asked them: "Did you find out
问他们 你们查出钱被送到哪里
Did they send Me the money, My rents, things?" Nothing!
他们有把这些钱 与我的房租 给我吗 什么都想不出来
"We don't know, Mother. We didn't see. We didn't bother."
我们不知道 母亲 我们没有去看 我们不在意
There should be alertness as to how much money is going where,
对于钱花到哪里去 付到哪里去
You go to an ashram, you ask them:
你去到静室 问他们
"Now, how much money you have got?"
现在 你们有多少钱
In short, you don't know how much money you have got.
简而言之 你们不知道有多少钱
"No, Mother, You know we went to that place,
不是 母亲 您知道我们去到那里
and then we bought twenty tins of fish,
买了二十罐鱼
so all money was exhausted." "But why?
所有的钱都花光了 但为什么
Why did you buy twenty tins of fish?"
为什么你们要买二十罐鱼
"Because the women said: 'You'd better buy twenty fish.'"
因为女士们说你们最好买 二十
"How many there are to eat?"
有多少人要吃
Like that, they have no idea, no alertness,
像这样 他们没有思想 没有警觉
nothing, it's all a mess.
什么都没有 一团糟
What time people get up, what time they sleep,
人们何时起床 何时就寝
what time, what they do; there is no alertness about it,
何时做什么事情 对这些都没有警觉
because in Sahaja Yoga you are your own guru.
在霎哈嘉瑜伽 你们是自己的导师
Everybody's guru. A Great Guru they are!
每个人的导师 他们都是伟大的导师
You are your own guru, no doubt,
你们是你们自己的导师 无庸置疑
but you must have that self-discipline.
但是你们要有自律
To be a guru you have to be
要成为导师 你们要自律
complete determination to rise higher,
有完全的决心去升进得更高
to ascend by whatever means it is possible,
用所有可能的方法升进
whatever is needed for your ascent.
并提供所有升进之所需
That's, is a sign of a person who will be a guru.
这是成为导师的人的预兆
There's no communication. There's a communication gap.
但是你们没有沟通 在沟通上有断层
There's no understanding of each other.
对彼此不了解
There are problems. There's no emotional
有问题存在
Another story I can tell you,
我可以告诉你们另一个故事
because I have been in Gandhiji's ashram.
因为我曾住在甘地的静室
Of course our ashram was nowhere like his.
当然 我们的静室一点也不像他的
His ashram was.. You had to get up at four o'clock,
在他的静室——你要在四点起床
take your bath with cold water,
用冷水沐浴
and go for the 'PRATHANA',
然后出外做祷告（Prathana）
and you would see all the snakes going round you.
你们会看见蛇到处爬行
And when you are doing your 'PRATHANA' there,
当你在那儿祈祷
all the snakes, somebody might be sitting before you,
所有的蛇——好像会坐在你前面
doing like that, with you. But most snakes never bit anyone.
和你一样在祈祷
You are not supposed to say anything.
你们不可说话
And best, this gentleman used to walk so fast,
这位绅士习惯走得很快
this Gandhiji, you see he was hardly he had any weight.
甘地 你看他几乎没有任何重量
So he used to just jump.
所以他习惯只是跳
That's how I learnt how to walk fast with him,
这是我如何学会快步走
because you had to walk, really run with him.
因为你必须走 眞的要和他一起跑
And then, the food was all boiled, without any salt.
所有食物都用水煮 不加盐
You could use salt if you wanted to,
你们可以用盐 如果你们想要的话
and then he would put some oil,
然后他会放些油
which you may not like so much. If you wanted,
但你们或许不喜欢这样 如果你们想要的话
you could have oil on top of that.
你们可以在食物上倒一些油
He said: "You must make your tongue all right.
他说 你们必须让你们的舌头良好
Why should your tongue ask for a particular type of a food?"
为什么你们的舌头要吃特定的食物
He was worse than Zen, I tell you!
他比禅宗还糟糕 我告诉你们
Even Zen tried that very much with his disciples.
禅宗多次用这种方法训练弟子
He used to make things which were bitter,
他会做一些苦涩的东西
like quinine raised to power a-hundred-and-eight.
味道苦出108倍
Then to compensate it, the sweet was sugar,
然后 作为补偿
so that your tongue is all right.
目的是要把你们的舌头变得良好
So the training of the tongue,
因此要训练舌头
then [INAUDIBLE] what you speak.
注意你们讲那些事情
What do you say, are you just chatting?
你们说些什么 还是你们是否只在聊天
You are a Sahaja Yogi.
你们是霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者
Every word you say is a mantra.
你们说的任何一个字都是口诀
These ashrams are much higher and greater than
这些静室比世界上所有的静室 都更崇高更伟大
Do you know that you are the instruments of God Almighty,
你们知道你们是全能的神的工具
and when you speak, every word of yours is a mantra?
当你们说话时 你们说的每个字都是口诀
Whatever is your desire is the command.
你们愿望的任何事都是命令
Unless and until you realize this, the alertness about it,
除非你们了解到这点 对此保持警觉
our ashrams are just like orphanages.
要不然我们的静室只会 是一座座孤儿院
People like a leader to be sweet, sweetie-pie,
人们想要领袖甜蜜 是个甜心饼
so that they can eat very well. The leader.
好让他们把领袖吃下
Or somebody overly strict comes in. He's another Hitler.
或是有个过度严格的人进驻 他是另一个希特勒
There's no discretion that you have to be strict,
没有明辨是非能力地 严格下去并没有用
at the same time you have to be loving, caring, protecting.
有的时候 你们要有爱心 照顾别人 保护别人
Many things can be said in humor.
很多事情可以用幽默的方式说出
That doesn't give such a sting to people.
那样做不会刺伤人
But a Sahaja Yogi should think,
霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者应该 要深深感到荣幸
that you have to do this or do that,
告诉他要做这个 做那个
that She's so much bothered about you, about your family,
她如此关怀你们的家庭
about your children, about your ashram.
你们的孩子 你们的静室
So that alertness should be also in the
这警觉性应该要在 静室的人的脑海中
how to talk, what to say.
如何谈吐 说些什么
You are the mouthpieces of God Almighty.
你们是全能神的代言人
How can you waste your time chatting?
你们怎能够浪费时间在聊天呢
So it is to be realized how to behave,
因此要了解作为神的代言人
for a person who is the mouthpiece of God.
要有什么样的举止
You represent Him, actually. How you should dress up,
你们事实上代表祂 你们应知道如何穿着
how you should walk, how you should sit, how you should eat.
应如何行走 应如何坐下 应如何饮食
I was surprised that people are drinking beer in the ashram.
我很惊讶人们 竟然在静室中喝啤酒
I mean, it is non-alcoholic.
我的意思是 这虽然不含酒精
But it's beer, made of molasses.
但这是由糖浆（molasses） 制成的啤酒
But, anyway, it is beer.
从任何方面来看它都是啤酒
How can you drink that molasses business?
你们怎么能够喝这糖浆的制品
Have you ever been near any sugar factory?
你们有否走近任何糖浆厂
The smell of the molasses! You are consuming that!
闻过那糖浆的味道吗 你们就在喝这种东西
So whatever you are eating, whatever you are spending,
所以无论你们吃些什么 花费些什么
whatever you are talking,
说些什么
I mean whatever is the extroversion, whatever is outside,
我的意思是无论什么是外在的 无论什么是外在的
must express your inside.
都必须在你们的内在表现出来
So you have to develop your Hamsa Chakra.
所以你们要发展你们的明善轮
Self-disciplining and introspection:
自律与自省
"Why do I do such a thing, I am a Sahaja Yogi?"
我为什么会做这样的事情 我是个霎哈嘉瑜伽修习者
Ask this question every morning,
每天早晚都问这个问题
and in the evening please note it down:
请把它写下来
"What did I do for Sahaja Yoga?"
我为霎哈嘉瑜伽做了些什么
We have fun. We have music. We have everything,
我们享乐 我们有音乐 我们拥有一切
but everything should be done in a dignified manner.
但每件事都要用 有尊严的态度去成就
Even dancing, I was saying, learn some rhythms.
甚至是跳舞 我的意思是要学一些韵律
Otherwise somebody's doing the trot and another is galloping.
要不然 有些人在小跑 另一些人在飞奔
That too like horses - looks so odd.
你们就像马一样——看起来真怪
There should be gentleness. There should be
你们应该要柔和
Learn more, how would you dance?
多学一点 你们会如何跳舞
Practise it. It's all right, in the house.
练习它 可以在屋子里练习
How the ladies should dance, how should they walk
女士们应该学如何跳舞 如何走路
because your whole expression
因为你们整个表现 就是全能神的展现
So how you should be among yourselves,
因此你们该如何身处于你们之中
how you should talk, when you should get up,
你们该如何交谈 你们该在什么时候起床
when you should sleep.
你们该在什么时候睡觉
Everything will change if you really become
每件事都会改变
who is the Source of discretion.
祂是明辨是非能力的源头
In discretion so many things you will learn.
在明辨之中你们学到许多的事情
The first is the tolerance. "It's all right.
首先是包容 没关系
We'll work it out. It will work out."
我们会解决它 这事会被解决
You will learn what is love, which is detached.
你们会学到什么是无执着的爱
You will learn what is humor,
你们会学到什么是幽默
which tickles but does not hurt.
搔到别人的痒处却不会伤害别人
You will learn also what to say in your lectures,
你们也将学会在你们的演讲上 该说些什么
what to listen to. And of all things,
该聆听些什么 在所有事之中
you will know how to fulfil the visions of God Almighty.
你们会知道如何 达成全能神的理想
Now today, I had to tell all these things, of course,
在今天 我必须要说这一切事情
But the other part of the Visshuddhi is that
喉轮的另一部分 是你们是整体的一部分
you are part and parcel of the whole,
是宇宙大我的一部分
So you have to be like oceans. Oceans in every way.
因此你们要像海洋 到处都是海洋
That's how you will realize that this ocean of yours
你们藉此将会明白你们的 海洋没有界线
but the beauty of the ocean and the creativity of the ocean.
海洋的美丽也没有界线 这海洋的创造力也没有界线
Everything is within you which you have to utilize,
一切都在你们内在之中
which you have to develop, to manifest.
你们要去运用 去发展 去展现出来
Because if you are part and parcel of Virat,
因为如果你们是宇宙大我的一部分
that you are the Virat, then how discreet you should be.
你们就是宇宙大我 那么你们要有怎样的明辨力呢
I hope all of you will know that
我希望你们全部都会知道
your behavior has to be of a level, not superficial,
你们的举止要有这水平 不肤浅
not cheapish, not greedy, of course not lusty;
不愚笨 不贪婪 当然不含色欲
but dignified, saintly, royal, magnificent,
而是要有尊严 神圣 高贵 杰出
beautiful and joy-giving.
美丽 并散发喜乐
May God bless you all.
愿神祝福你们